<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>Introduction to CMGUI</title>
    <section>
        <title>CMGUI: The Windows</title>
        <para>In order to become acquainted with the features of CMGUI, it is useful to run through
            some of the simple example files provided. CMGUI is a command line driven program, and
            all of its features are available via a command line interface – however, it also
            provides a more accessible GUI interface allowing many (but not all!) of these commands
            to be executed via a more familiar graphical interface. The interface is broken up into
            a number of windows that allow access to the different functions of the program. The
            first example will familiarise you with the most commonly used windows.</para>
        <para>The CMGUI examples can be obtained from the CMISS website at
            http://cmiss.bioeng.auckland.ac.nz/development/examples/a/index_thumbs.html. These
            examples normally consist of a comfile and some other data files for creating a mesh.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Example a1 – Graphical Element Groups – Viewing a Cube</title>
            <para>Load CMGUI to begin the first example. The first window that will present itself
                when loading CMGUI is the command window. This window has a selection of menus and
                three functional areas; a history area which shows commands that have been executed,
                a command line where commands may be entered directly, and an output area that shows
                the text output of any commands, including error and help messages. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>The CMGUI main window</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="mainWindow.png" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>The CMGUI main window</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>In the file menu, go to Open > Com file, then locate the example-a1.com file. This
                is a text file containing all the commands used in this example, as well as useful
                comments on what the various commands are doing. You will see the comfile window
                appear, displaying the file you have just loaded. All the lines that begin with a #
                character are explanatory comments, the rest are commands. The comfile window has
                three buttons at the bottom - the “All” button executes the entire comfile, while
                the “Selected” button will execute only selected portions. “Close” closes the
                comfile. Individual commands from the comfile can be executed by double clicking on
                them – notice that clicking to select a command in the comfile window makes that
                command appear in the command line panel in the command window, and clicking again
                then executes it. It is important to note that the order the commands are executed
                in can be important, especially in later examples, so click on the commands in the
                order they appear in the example comfile.</para>
            <para>Double-click the first two commands in the comfile – a new window will appear,
                displaying a wireframe representation of a cube. This is the graphics window. You
                can rotate, zoom and translate the view of the cube in this window by holding down
                the left, right and middle mouse buttons respectively while moving the mouse in the
                display area. Have a go at moving the cube around, and click the “perspective”
                button on and off to see the difference it makes to the display. To reset the view,
                click the “View All” button.</para>
            <para>Once you have run through all of the commands in this example (either by
                double-clicking them or by using the “All” button in the comfile window) you should
                have a blue, somewhat shiny cube, a set of blue axes, and red numbers at each corner
                of the cube. These are the numbers of the nodes, the points that make up the 3D
                model. Another window will also have appeared, called the “Node Viewer”. This window
                allows you to manipulate the data that define the nodes – in this case the corners
                of the cube. In the cube example, each node has a number and coordinates. You can
                click on each of these buttons (at this stage a small GUI bug means you need to
                manually resize the window after clicking) to show editable boxes containing the
                actual data contained in the nodes. This window therefore allows direct access to
                the node data for editing. If you edit coordinate data and click the “Apply” button,
                you will see changes in the shape of the cube in the graphics window. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Other Interface Windows: Editors</title>
            <para>That is the end of the example file commands, but there are other windows you can
                now use to manipulate the cube shown in the graphics window. Go into the Graphics
                menu in the Command Window, and select “Material editor”. This brings up a window
                that allows you to create and edit materials, which define the appearance of objects
                in the graphics window. You can manipulate the colour, specularity (shininess),
                emitted light (glow), and alpha (transparency) of a material using this window. Your
                edited material is used to create the sphere in the preview panel at the bottom of
                the window – you may need to resize the window in order to get a good sized preview
                panel. Click on some of the already defined materials in the list at the top to see
                how they affect the preview sphere, then play around with the sliders to alter the
                material. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>The material editor window</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="materialEditorWindow.png" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>The material editor window</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Click on the material “bluey” – this is the material used to show the faces of the
                cube in this first example, as defined in the comfile. Use the colour and property
                sliders to make it quite different; perhaps red and highly transparent, then click
                “Apply” to change the cube in the graphics window to your new material.</para>
            <para>Now close the material editor and go to the Graphics menu, selecting “Scene
                editor”. The scene editor allows you to manipulate which objects appear in the
                graphics window, and how they are rendered. It also allows you to create new
                objects, as well as change their order in the scene, which is particularly important
                when rendering transparent objects. As a quick example of what can be done with this
                editor, select the “lines” setting in the settings list (shown selected below), and
                un-tick the check box. The white lines along the edges of the cube will disappear in
                the graphics window. Similarly, you can choose whether to show the cubes surfaces or
                the node numbers using the appropriate check boxes. You will notice that as you
                select settings (such as surfaces) in the settings list, their properties will
                appear in the settings editor below. Using this editor you can change a large number
                of the display properties of objects in the scene. There are many more important
                functions to this editor window which will be explained in more depth later. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>The scene editor window</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="sceneEditorWindow.png" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>The scene editor window</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>CMGUI Architecture</title>
        <section>
            <title>Regions and Fields</title>
            <para>The basic structural unit in CMGUI is called a *region* - region is a container
                for the objects representing a model. Regions own a set of fields and may contain
                child regions, thereby allowing a hierarchical model structure. For example, you may
                have a "body" region that contains "heart", "lung", and "stomach" regions..</para>
            <para>When you start CMGUI, a *root region* exists; this is an empty space into which
                other regions are loaded. When you load in exnode and exelem files, a new region
                will be created in the *root region* named for the group declared in the files. For
                example, if you were to load in heart.exnode and heart.exelem files which declare a
                group "heart" (via the line ``Group name: heart``), a new region called "heart"
                would be created containing all the nodes, elements and fields defined in these
                files.</para>
            <para>Each region contains a set of *fields* from which a model is built up. A field is
                a function that returns values over a domain; for example, the "potential" field
                could provide a value for the electrical potential of each point in the heart
                domain, which could be a finite element mesh. The geometry of the heart is itself
                defined by the coordinate field (this field is often called "coordinates" in our
                models). Finite element fields in CMGUI are generally defined by storing discrete
                parameters at nodes (eg the coordinates of the node, the electrical potential at
                each node) and interpolated across the *xi space* spanned by elements to give the
                continuous field.</para>
            <para>Other examples of fields include fibre orientation in the heart, temperature,
                pressure, material properties, strain and so on. In CMGUI you can also define fields
                that are computed from other fields. For example, you might define a field called
                "scaled_coordinates" by scaling coordinates x, y, and z to x, y, and 10z, perhaps to
                exaggerate the height of topological features. You might also compute strain from
                deformed and undeformed coordinates, fibre axis from fibre Euler angles, and so
            on.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Other data in CMGUI</title>
            <para> The structure of the CMGUI *command data* (that is, the complete set of data used
                by CMGUI) is divided into a number of *containers* and categories. Besides the
                regions which contain fields, there are also the following lists and managers, which
                contain other data used to create visualizations:</para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Scene manager - scenes contain definitions of how to display
                            visualizations. The region created when you load exnode and exelem data
                            (such as the heart region described above) is used to automatically
                            create a graphical representation in scene "default" when loaded. Scenes
                            contains either (1) graphical renditions of regions (2) graphics objects
                            (3) child scenes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Graphical material manager - contains a list of graphical materials
                            that can be applied to graphical representations or objects.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Texture manager - contains a list of textures that can be used in
                            material definitions or volume renderings, etc. Textures are 2D or 3D
                            images.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Spectrum manager - contains a list of spectra that can be used in
                            material definitions. These control how the graphical material is
                            changed when graphics are coloured by a data field.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Graphics object list - contains simple graphics objects which are not
                            tied to a model representation, but can be drawn in a scene. These can
                            animate with time.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Glyph list - contains glyphs that can be used to represent data points
                            in the graphics window - such things as spheres, cubes, arrows, axes,
                            points or lines. Objects from the graphics objects list may be added to
                            the glyph list, in order to create customized glyphs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>CMGUI is not like most common software packages that can save a single file
                containing all of your work. In CMGUI, the data being worked on is often loaded in
                as a number of separate files, and the editing of the visual representation of this
                data often does not change it; it only alters how it is represented in the 3D
                window. Currently, it is not possible to save your work in a single file that can be
                loaded in order to recreate all your work on the representation. For example; if you
                load in a model, change the viewpoint, alter the materials used to render it, and
                add glyphs to important data points, there is no way to simply "save" all of these
                changes from a simple menu item. There are ways to save all these changes but this
                will be covered in another section.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</article>
